<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A preparation vnto fasting and repentance. By Peter Moulin, and translated by I.B.</title>
            <title>Preparation à jeune et repentance. English</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7336.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113623</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848855</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848855</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176715</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12526)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176715)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 643:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A preparation vnto fasting and repentance. By Peter Moulin, and translated by I.B.</title>
                  <title>Preparation à jeune et repentance. English</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
                  <author>J. B. (John Bulteel), d. 1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[108] p. ; 12mo.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. S[nodham] for Nathaniel Newbery, and are to be sould at the signe of the Starre vnder S. Peters Church in Cornehill, and in Popes head ally,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.B. = John Bulteel.</note>
                  <note>Printer's full name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The Folger Shakespeare Library copy has two settings of the title page: with "B" in line 6 under and between the "L" of "Moulin" (A2r) and with the "B" in line 6 under the "N" of "Moulin" (E12r; possibly intended as a cancel)--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶ B-E¹² .</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 7336a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fasting --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176715:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176715:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176715:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176715:2"/>
            <p>A PREPARATION vnto FASTING and REPENTANCE.</p>
            <p>By PETER MOVLIN, and tranſlated by <hi>I. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery,</hi> and are to be ſould at the ſigne of the Starre vnder <hi>S. Peters</hi> Church in Cornehill, and in Popes head ally. 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176715:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176715:3"/>
            <head>To the Religious and Vertuous Lady, the Lady IANE BOYS, Widdow to the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Sir IOHN BOYS, ſometime Recorder of the City of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> grace &amp; peace from our LORD IESVS CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adame,</hi> I preſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips view and reading, this Homelie preached in the
<pb facs="tcp:176715:4"/> French tongue by that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and iudicious diuine, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Peter du Moulin,</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the word of God, and by me tranſlated, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that excellent conference betweene God and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Abraham;</hi> wherein we may behold on the one ſide the nature of ſinne, and the vengeance of God when ſinners are come to their full meaſure; on the other ſide the patience and famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar acceſſe, which he affords to thoſe that loue him, how milde and patient he is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that feare him, and how hee behaues him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe towards his enemies,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:4"/> and all to this end to moue vs all to faith, repentance, and humility.</p>
            <p>And ſithence my ſmall paines in engliſhing it yeelds me a right to make choyce of one to whom I may dedicate this little volume, I am bold to preſent the ſame vnto your Ladiſhip (hoping your fauourable acceptance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) and the rather becauſe it befits you, (Madame) in many reſpects, for theſe vertues that are here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, are in you. (Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame) I ſpeake it without flattery; faith, repentance, humility, zeale to Gods houſe, loue to his word, loue
<pb facs="tcp:176715:5"/> and faith which you haue to the Lord Ieſus, and towards all his Saints; for you are an <hi>Anna,</hi> alwayes ſeruing God in the Temple with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and prayers, a <hi>Lydia</hi> in hearing Gods word, a <hi>Mary</hi> in pondering and meditating the ſame, a <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas</hi> to Widdowes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans, a <hi>Shunamite</hi> to the Prophets and Miniſters of God, not onely countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing our perſons and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery with your perſon and preſence in our Church of <hi>Canterbury</hi> when you are here, but alſo cheriſhing vs with good and comfortable words, and exerciſing your
<pb facs="tcp:176715:5"/> liberall charitie towards our poore, not leeſing your firſt loue, like the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> but continuing it towards vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time; and therefore the iuſt God will not forget your piety towards him, nor your charity towards his Saints; but as your name and charitable workes are inregiſtred in our booke of remembrance, ſo is your name written in the Booke of Life, your deeds of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in feeding, couering, viſiting the poore, written in that Booke that ſhall be opened in the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to your conſolation; then ſhall you reape plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:176715:6"/> what you ſowe here, and as <hi>Damaſcen</hi> ſpeakes, here you giue a little, there you ſhall receiue much; now you giue a tranſitory thing, then ſhall you gaine an eternall; here you giue a penny, there you ſhall receiue a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; for if <hi>Iulius Ceſar</hi> gaue Lands to one that gaue him but a draught of water, what a reward will Chriſt giue to thoſe, that giue but a cup of water to drinke in his name to thoſe that belong to him? If <hi>Darius</hi> gaue a Kingdome to <hi>Siloſontes,</hi> that gaue him a garment onely; what a Kingdome will Chriſt giue to thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:176715:6"/> giue him cloathing, foode, and drinke, in the name and perſon of the leaſt and poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of his brethren? The ſame Ieſus Chriſt whom you feede, cloath, and viſite here on earth in his members; as he feedes you and cloathes you here on earth, not onely corporally, but alſo ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, with the ſpirituall <hi>Manna</hi> the bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life, euen he himſelfe who is your ſpirituall foode and garment alſo, will giue you that euerlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, prepared for you from the foundation of the world; where and when you ſhall be crowned with the crowne
<pb facs="tcp:176715:7"/> of righteouſneſſe, cloathed with the roabes of glory, ſit downe with <hi>Abraham, Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> to be nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the fruit of the tree of life and water of life, and liue eternally with him in the kingdome of heauen, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Canterbury <date>the 30. of Iune, 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips in all dutifull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to command, IOHN BVLTEEL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:176715:7"/>
            <head>¶ A Preparation vnto FASTING and REPENTANCE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>GEN. Chap. 18. verſ. 20. 21. 22. 23. 24. 25. &amp;c.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>20</bibl> 
                     <hi>And the Lord ſaide, Becauſe the cry of Sodome and Gomorrah is great, and becauſe their Sinne is very grieuous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>21</bibl> 
                     <hi>I will goe downe now, and ſee whether they haue done altogether according to the cry of it, which is come vnto mee, and if not, I will know, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not needfull my brethren to repreſent &amp; ſhew forth vnto you the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb facs="tcp:176715:8"/> occaſions, for the which we are inuited to afflict our ſoules, and ſanctifie a Faſt by Repentance; ſeeing that we want not ordinary cauſes: The enmity of Satan, and of the world, the feebleneſſe of the Church, the Name of God blaſphemed, our vices that doe increaſe, our zeale which waxeth cold, the hand of God lifted vp to ſtrike vs, and his rods prepared, doe binde vs to tremble vnder his hand, and preuent his iudgements by Faſting and Repentance; leaſt GOD ſend vs another kinde of Faſting, making vs to Faſt from his Word, which is the ſpirituall bread, ſending vs that famine prophecied by the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> not a
<pb facs="tcp:176715:8"/> famine of bread, but a famine of the hearing of the Word of God, for a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe we taſte this ſpiritual bread with diſtaſte, and receiue not his Word with reuerence.</p>
               <p>Let vs doe in ſuch ſort, that our humiliation may be acceptable vnto God, and that whiles our bodies are voide of meate, we haue not our hearts repleniſhed with hatred and rancour, that whiles wee abſtaine from drinking, we be not drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with pride: (for God doth as much deteſt the faſt of the hypocrite, as the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutenes of the prophane;) that our mouthes doe not only abſtaine from meates, but alſo from bad diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:176715:9"/> and euill words; that we faſt with our eares, to keepe them ſhut againſt vaine and idle diſcourſes, and with our hands, keeping vs from ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine &amp; vſury: In a word, that al that which is in vs, euen to our ſecret thoughts celebrat vnto God an holy Faſt, and pleaſing vnto God, through Ieſus Chriſt. That we may know that faſting is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted to ſatisfie the Iuſtice of God, but to reuenve vs of our ſelues. That we giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poore that which wee ſpare &amp; take from our ſelues, that our voluntary faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may helpe and aide that faſt which the poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth of force &amp; neceſſitie. And while that your bodies faſt, let your ſoules feede on
<pb facs="tcp:176715:9"/> the foode of life, which is a meate which you muſt eate (as of olde the Paſchall Lambe) with bitter hearbes, ſoaking it in teares of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Inſtead of ſackcloth, after the faſhion of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, be ye cloathed and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered all euer with holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and integritie; in lieu of ſprinckling of aſhes, as of olde, acknowledge your ſelues, with <hi>Abraham,</hi> to be duſt and aſhes, and giue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to GOD, in humbling your ſelues: Who knoweth if God will not haue pitty on his people, and will not ſtirre vp his compaſſions vpon his children? For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in times paſt ſtaied the Sunne at the prayer of one man, how much more will
<pb facs="tcp:176715:10"/> he ſtay and keepe backe his iudgements at the generall cry of his whole Church, proceeding from faith, and made ſtrong by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance?</p>
               <p>To diſpoſe our hearts thereunto, I haue choſen this excellent conference betweene God and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Abraham;</hi> where you ſee on the one ſide the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſinne, and the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God when ſins are come to their full &amp; heaped meaſure: on the other ſide the patience and familiar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe which hee affords to thoſe that loue him. All this conference may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to theſe three heads: I. Who he is that ſpeakes. II. How hee behaues him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:176715:10"/> towards his enemies. III. How milde and patient hee is towards them that feare him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. PART.</head>
               <head>I. Who he is that ſpeakes.</head>
               <p>TOuching him that ſpeakes vnto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> it is ſaid in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Chapter, that three men did preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to <hi>Abraham;</hi> one of thoſe is called a while after the LORD: And ſo in the hiſtory of the viſion of the burning buſh, and in the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Gideon,</hi> and in that of the conception of <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> euen he who is called an Angell, is called the LORD; which cannot appertaine
<pb facs="tcp:176715:11"/> vnto any but vnto the Son of God our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: For it is hee, who being ſent of God, is not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding God, and the Lord our righteouſneſſe, <hi>Ieremie</hi> 23. by whom euen then the Lord gouerned his Church, made it feele his aſſiſtance and know his wil; yea, before the floud hee hath by the mouth of <hi>Noah</hi> preached to the dead, whole ſpirits are now in the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall priſon. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19.</p>
               <p>Perhaps you finde it ſtrange that hee appeared vnto <hi>Abraham</hi> in the forme of a man, as if before he was borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> he had tooke mans nature; but you muſt know that the bodies wherein the Son
<pb facs="tcp:176715:11"/> of God appeared in the olde Teſtament, were but bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed bodies for a time and by diſpenſation, the Deity of the Sonne not being vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted perſonally to the body, which was an inſtrument which he vſed for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent action onely, and then left it. Euen as a good or a bad Angel may aſſume a body and moue it, without giuing it life or forme, and without making himſelfe one perſon with that body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II. How God behaues him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe towards his enemies.</head>
               <p>NOw touching the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wherein and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God behaueth himſelfe towards his enemies, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb facs="tcp:176715:12"/> vnto vs in theſe words: <hi>And the Lord ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Abraham, Becauſe the cry of Sodom and Gomorrah is great, &amp; becauſe their ſin is very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, I will goe downe now, and ſee whether they haue done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together according to the crie of it, which is come vnto me, and if not, I will know.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where you ſee, that God beares and permits with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience the wicked to rule a long time, but when their ſinne is come to the full, then he vnfolds and ſpreads abroad his terrible iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; which he doth here in this place after an inquiry and kinde of information, to ſhew that he proceedes herein iuſtly and without precipitation. Hee ſpeakes
<pb facs="tcp:176715:12"/> then of a ſin that cries before God, ſo <hi>Abels bloud,</hi> Gen. 4. <hi>cryeth from the ground vnto God for vengeance;</hi> So <hi>Iob</hi> in the 31. chapter, ſpeaking of land detained by an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt poſſeſſor, ſaith, that <hi>the land cryes againſt the vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full poſſeſſor, and the furrowes likewiſe therof complaint.</hi> And <hi>Habbakuk</hi> Chap. 2. ſpeaking of houſes built by extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaith, that <hi>the ſtones cryes out of the wall, and the beame out of the timber anſwereth it,</hi> as bearing witneſſe againſt their maſter before God. And Saint <hi>Iames</hi> in his fiſt chapter, ſaith, that the hyre of the labourers, which haue reaped downe your fieldes, which is of you kept backe by fraud, cryeth, and
<pb facs="tcp:176715:13"/> the cryes of them which haue reaped, are entred into the eares of the Lord of Sabbath. Which teacheth vs, that there are heinous ſins that cry and call God to veangeance, ſo that though men ſhould holde their peace, the thing it ſelfe would ſpeake, as our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaith, Luke 19. <hi>If theſe men ſhould hold their peace, the ſtones would immediately cry out.</hi> For euen as when God ſpeakes, the liueleſſe and ſenceleſſe things vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: When he ſpeakes to the rocke, it caſteth foorth water; when he ſpeakes to the dead, they riſe vp at his word: Euen ſo God vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the language of ſenceleſſe things, and brings
<pb facs="tcp:176715:13"/> them foorth to witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them whom hee will puniſh in his wrath. Theſe crying ſinnes are the ſinnes that are come to their full meaſure, as the iniquitie of the Amorites in <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> time; for in <hi>Abrahams</hi> time God declareth in the 15. chapter of Geneſis, that <hi>the iniquitie of the Amorites was not yet full,</hi> that is to ſay, that the meaſure was not full to the top as then; according to that which Chriſt Ieſus ſaith vnto the Iewes, Mat. 23 <hi>Ye fill vp the meaſure of your fathers:</hi> which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. ſaith, happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his time, <hi>They fill vp their ſinnes alwayes, for the wrath is come vpon them to the vttermoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176715:14"/>
               <p>This laſt period of ſinnes, is when theſe two things concurre in a countrey or in a twone: I. When ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers doe boaſt of their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked acts, and haue loſt that good that remaines in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>to wit,</hi> the ſhame of doing euill, wherein the Prophet <hi>Eſayas</hi> coupleth the Iewes with the Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, in the 3. chapter, <hi>They declare their ſinne as Sodome, they hide it not</hi> Such are they of whom the <hi>Wiſe-man</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the 2. Chapter of Prouerbes, <hi>who reioyce to doe euil, and delight in the froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the wicked,</hi> which is the third and laſt degree of iniquitie, which <hi>Dauid</hi> deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth in the 1. Pſal. name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>to ſit in the ſeat of the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176715:14"/> that is to ſay, of thoſe that with inſolency and flowting do mocke at Gods Word, and take a delight, yea, a glory to deſpight and vexe him. II. The ſecond point that makes this full meaſure of ſinne is, when there is no one man to be found in a citie or countrey that withſtands the euill, and oppoſeth himſelfe againſt it, and as it is ſaid in the 12. Pſalme, <hi>The godly man cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, the faithfull faile from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the children of men,</hi> there is none that doth good, no not one; none that feare GOD, no not one; or elſe the number of good men is ſo ſmall that they are as nothing in a crowde, and as a graine of
<pb facs="tcp:176715:15"/> corne in a heape of ſtraw. Such was the condition of Ieruſalem, which <hi>Ieremie</hi> deplores in his 5. Chapter, <hi>Runne yee to and fro through the ſtreetes of Ieruſalem and ſee now, and know, and ſeeke in the broad places thereof, if ye can finde a man, if there be any that executeth iudgement, that ſeeketh the truth, and I will pardon it.</hi> And in the 22. chapter of <hi>Ezekiel, I ſought for a man amongſt them that ſhould make vp the hedge, and ſtand in the gappe before me for the land, that I ſhould not deſtroy it, but I found none; therefore haue I powred out mine indignation vpon them, I haue conſumed them with the fire of my wrath, their owne way haue I recompenſed vpon
<pb facs="tcp:176715:15"/> their heads, ſaith the Lord God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſelfe ſame enormitie and hainouſneſſe of ſinne is here repreſented by the word, aggrauate, or made heauy and weighing down, where God ſaith, that the ſinne of Sodome is very grieuous, ſpeaking of ſinnes as of burthens, which ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme our ſoules, and doe hinder them to lift vp them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to God, and doe caſt them downe headlong into the depth of perdition: Or elſe he ſpeakes of ſinnes, as of weights put in a ballance, that carry them againſt the patience of God, and doe make his will to hang to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſide of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; therefore the Prophet
<pb facs="tcp:176715:16"/> 
                  <hi>Zacharie</hi> in his fift Chapter compares ſin to a lumpe of lead; and the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> Pſa. 38. ſaith, <hi>his iniquities are gone ouer his head, as an heauy burthen, they are too heauy for him:</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaking of our ſinnes as of heauy burthens, wherewith Ieſus Chriſt hath charged himſelfe to diſcharge vs; <hi>He hath borne our griefes, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried our ſorrowes, the Lord hath laid on him the iniquity of vs all</hi> and <hi>S. Peter,</hi> 1 Pet 2. <hi>He hath borne our ſinnes in his owne body on the tree, by whoſe ſtripes we are healed.</hi> O how heauy was that burthen, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the leaſt peece of our ſinnes which euery one of vs doe commit, is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient weight to caſt vs down
<pb facs="tcp:176715:16"/> headlong, and plunge vs to the bottome of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit! Now Ieſus Chriſt hath borne the ſinnes of all men on his Croſſe. It was the moſt principall burthen and charge of <hi>Ionas</hi> ſhippe; the Marriners laboured with ſtrength of armes to vnload the ſhip, &amp; to ſaue their liues did caſt their wares into the ſea, but the heauieſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then remained in the ſhip, namely <hi>Ionas</hi> ſinne; neither was there any way to ſaue themſelues, but by caſting him into the ſea. True it is, that as Leapers doe not feele nor ſmell their owne infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor they that haue an obſtructed and corrupt noſe doe not ſmell the ſcent of their breath; and the ſwine
<pb facs="tcp:176715:17"/> wallowing in the mire doe finde that odour ſweet; ſo men plunged and ſteeped in ſinne, feele not the weight of their ſinnes, becauſe they are as it were borne and bred with them, and that this naturall euill groweth and increaſeth more and more by cuſtome; which is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which the Philoſophers doe render, why thoſe that ſwimme betweene two wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, feele not the weight of the water which is ouer their heads, becauſe (ſay they) that an element is not heauy in his naturall place: Euen ſo ſinne doth not oppreſſe nor ouercharge the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of prophane men, and they feele not their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences burthened, becauſe ſin
<pb facs="tcp:176715:17"/> is there in them as in his own naturall place, but if God withdraweth a man out from this bottome and depth, and maketh him once to breath the aire of his grace, then the very reliques of ſin that are in him weighes him much downe and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries him much.</p>
               <p>When therefore the ſinne of the wicked is come to his full and laſt meaſure, then God, who by his patience hath inuited ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, who hath vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, dunged, and pruned this barren figge-tree three yeares long, finally ſeeing that it bringeth forth no fruit, and that the ſinner mocks at his long patience, commands that the are be
<pb facs="tcp:176715:18"/> laid vnto the roote of this curſed tree, and rewardeth his long expectation with the greatneſſe of his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Euen as when a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man condemned to death by law being found with childe, her execution is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred till ſhe be deliuered of of her childe; ſo although God hath already determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his councell to puniſh ſome wicked men, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he ſtayes till the ſin which they haue conceiued in their hearts, be brought to ripeneſſe; during which time the ſinner often makes merry, as malefactors doe, who to driue themſelues from their dumpes, play in priſon at cards and dice; but before God the day and
<pb facs="tcp:176715:18"/> houre of their execution is decreed.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding before he comes to that point, hee ſpeakes as if he doubted of the truth, and prepares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to make a kinde of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and enqueſt. <hi>I wil goe downe and ſee now,</hi> ſaith he) <hi>whether they haue done altogether according to the cry of it, which is come vnto me:</hi> And ſo in the confuſion of languages God deſcends, to ſee what the children of men builded, and to haue knowledge thereof.</p>
               <p>Theſe things are ſaid af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the faſhion of men, for God deſcends not, ſeeing he is euery where, and hath no need to enquire, ſeeing hee knoweth all things; but
<pb facs="tcp:176715:19"/> the holy Ghoſt ſtuttereth with vs, as with children, in humane words, of Diuine things. God comes downe to vs, when he makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be felt of vs; he ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth his arme, when he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playes his ſtrength; hee moues himſelfe when hee will mooue vs; he wakens when he makes it knowne that he hath not ſlept; hee enquires of the ſinnes of men, when he will conuict and conuince them; hee ſpeakes as doubting, when he will put vs out of doubt of the certainty and full knowledge of our actions.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding God giueth by this practiſe a rule vnto Magiſtrates, not to iudge till after a carefull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:19"/> and after a ripe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and to vndergoe that Law which God hath impoſed vnto himſelfe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I will goe now downe and ſee if it be thus and thus: Which is alſo a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to all particular men, that they be not vniuſtly prone to beleeue calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, nor raſhly vniuſt to condemne others without being well informed of the truth; but expecting the iudgement of GOD that will make all things mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, let vs beware that wee giue not raſhly our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:176715:20"/>
               <head>III. How gentle and milde God is towards them that feare him, and the care hee hath of his children.</head>
               <p>THe third point is the manner, how God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haues himſelfe towards thoſe that feare him. This point requires a more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe it toucheth vs more particularly.</p>
               <p>Of theſe three men ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues forwards towards Sodome; two of them goe on their way, but the third who is called the Lord, ſtayes with <hi>Abraham</hi> who being in thought for his nephew <hi>Lot,</hi> fearing leaſt he ſhould be intrapped and
<pb facs="tcp:176715:20"/> inwrapped in the ruine and deſtruction of Sodome, makes interceſſion for the men thereof: <hi>Wilt thou alſo deſtroy the righteous with the wicked? ſhall not the iudge of all the earth doe right?</hi> Hee could not better ground his ſupplication, then on Gods Iuſtice as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. What ſhall we ſay, is God vnrighteous who taketh vengeance? God forbid, for then how ſhall God iudge the world? God being by nature righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it ſelfe, can no more do iniuſtice, then white can black, or the flame can freez. To ſay that God is vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, is to ſay hee is God and is not God, for to be, and to be righteous, are one
<pb facs="tcp:176715:21"/> thing with God, not as with men, or Angels, who are ſuſceptible of contrary qualities without corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſubſtance. Euen as the right of gouerning and of iudging the world, is deuolued and fallen to him by inheritance, not happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by election: ſo neither is he iuſt and righteous to be conformable to lawes that any hath impoſed to him, but as his Empire, ſo his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is naturall.</p>
               <p>This righteouſneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neceſſarily ioyned with goodneſſe, <hi>Abraham</hi> had reaſon to preſuppoſe, that it was more conuenient and befitting this vpright good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to ſupport the wicked for the good mens ſake,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:21"/> then to deſtroy the good for the wickeds ſake. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it ſeemes this beares many exceptions, and hath many difficulties. For not to ſpeake of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Gods cauſe, which befall the faithfull alone, while that the vngodly proſper as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Yee ſhall weepe, but the world ſhall reioyce,</hi> becauſe theſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are honourable, a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reproach, honeſt brands &amp; blemiſhes, ſcarfe, and liueries of our warfare, and conformities to Ieſus Chriſt, I will ſpeake onely of euils and afflictions wherewith God puniſheth the good with the wicked, and that becauſe of the wicked: God had foretolde
<pb facs="tcp:176715:22"/> by his Prophets, that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſins of the people, the land ſhould vomit out her Inhabitants, which was fulfilled when <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> did lead the people cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue into Babylon; with the multitude of this rebellious people, <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> were led alſo away, as alſo thoſe three men, who by the heate of their faith, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the heate of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning furnace. There were the good afflicted, for the wicked mens ſake. There were ſeauen thouſand in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, and among the ten tribes, that had not bowed their knees vnto <hi>Baal,</hi> were thoſe exempted from the publicke calamitie, when as <hi>Salmanazar</hi> &amp; <hi>Tiglatpilezer</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176715:22"/> kings of Syria did leade the ten tribes into captiuitie. Doth not God ſay by his Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Chap. 21. that <hi>his ſword ſhall cut off from the land of Iſrael, the righteous and the wicked.</hi> And when God ſaith in the 18. Chapter of the Reuelation, <hi>Come out of Babylon my people that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes, and that ye receiue not of her plagnes?</hi> doth hee not warne them, that if any of his people remaine there, he ſhall be partaker of the plagues of Babylon? And if God would now at this time afflict a kingdome, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ouer to idolatry, and ſhould finde there a generall plague, who doubts but that the faithfull mixt with the
<pb facs="tcp:176715:23"/> Idolaters ſhould incurre the ſame danger?</p>
               <p>To explaine vnto you this point. Obſerue that when God viſits a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or a Citie, with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affliction, by reaſon of the wickedneſſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then thoſe of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, mixt with the wicked ſhall eſcape, whom God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to make as yet vſe of, and to imploy them for his glory, and for the good of his Church. So hee ſaued <hi>Noah</hi> from the vniuerſall Floud; becauſe hee would reſerue him, and make vſe of him, for the preſeruation of mankinde. So alſo in the dayes of the Emperour <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> the Church of the Apoſtles that was in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:23"/> was warned to goe out of the Citie, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw her ſelfe to Pella on the other ſide of Iordan, leaſt ſhee ſhould be inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the enemies in the beſieging of the Citie, whereby it was razed down and the people deſtroyed. And in the 14. Chapter of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> God ſpeakes after this manner: <hi>Sonne of man, when the land ſinneth againſt my by treſpaſſing grieuouſly, then will I ſtretch out mine hand vpon it, and will breake the ſtaffe of the bread thereof, and will ſend famine vpon it, and will cut off man and beaſt from it; though thoſe three men,</hi> Noah, Daniel, <hi>and</hi> Iob <hi>were in it, they ſhould deliuer but their owne ſoules by their
<pb facs="tcp:176715:24"/> righteouſneſſe, ſaith the Lord God; they ſhall not deliuer nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſonnes nor daughters, they onely ſhall be deliuered;</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the conſeruation of theſe men was profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Church of God.</p>
               <p>But if God, who prouides for his worke as it pleaſeth him, will imploy no more ſuch a one, and will quickly giue him the poſſeſſion of eternall life, then maruell not if he die as the reſt doe; and if the like and ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble accidents do befall him; notwithſtanding in his common afflictions with the wicked, he hath parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular conſolation; God giues him grace to profit by his chaſtiſements, and to take theſe baniſhments for
<pb facs="tcp:176715:24"/> flights from the world, and walking towards God: Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty is vnto him a whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and profitable dyer, and an exerciſe of abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence. In his death-bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſickeneſſe, Gods Angel aſſiſts him, who wipes off from him his ſweaty drops of bloud, and Chriſt Ieſus neere him ſhewing him the crowne of Glory. His death is as farre different from the death of others, as there is difference betweene the gates of hell, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. So Threſhers with the ſame flaile doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like threſh both the corne and the ſtraw, but to diuers endes; which are as Chriſt Ieſus ſaith, To gather the Wheate into the Barne, but
<pb facs="tcp:176715:25"/> to binde the ſtraw in bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, to burne it in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire. So the paſſage through the red Sea, was the ruine of the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, but was to the Church of God a paſſage to arriue vnto the promiſed inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. In a word, the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements wherewith God doth viſite the faithfull, ſhall neuer be fully diſtinct and ſeparated from thoſe of the wicked before the day of iudgement; for then the ſheepe ſhall be called out from among the goates, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided and ſet a part, and the tares growen pell-mell, and confuſedly mingled with Wheate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that hath toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endured both ſtorme and weather, winde and
<pb facs="tcp:176715:25"/> havle, ſhall be picked vp by the Angels, euen vnto the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry laſt ſlip and ſprig, and be bound in bottles, to be caſt into the euerlaſting fire.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> might ſeeme to paſſe the limits of modeſty in this demaund, as ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule the actions of God, <hi>Wilt thou</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>deſtroy the righteous with the wicked? that be farre from thee;</hi> as ſhewing vnto God his duty. Then afterwards hee ſeemes to vſe policy and Art to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, endeuouring to obtaine of God by retaile and parcels, that which hee thinkes hee ſhall not get by the whole, and all at one time; ſaying, <hi>If there be fifty righteous in the Citie, wilt thou
<pb facs="tcp:176715:26"/> notſpare the place for the fifty righteous that are therein?</hi> And this being granted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, from fifty he comes to forty fiue, and from that to forty, and from that to thirty, and ſo at laſt vnto ten. Hardly I ſuppoſe is there to be found any Prince, be hee neuer ſo meane and pettie, that would endure that any of his ſeruants ſhould leade him ſo by degrees, and abuſe thus his gentleneſſe, and yet notwithſtanding there is ſome compariſon betweene the greateſt Prince of the world, and the meaneſt beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, yea, betweene the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenteſt Angell, and betweene the Piſmire and worme, the diſtance and inequalitie is not infinite, for they are crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:26"/> and there can be no infinite diſtance betwixt two finite things; but there is no compariſon betweene God and the moſt excellent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that is; how much leſſe betweene God and between a man, a ſinner as <hi>Abraham</hi> was, who acknowledgeth himſelfe to be nought but duſt and aſhes? whoſe light is nought but darkeneſſe? whoſe righteouineſſe is as filthy ragges? whoſe ſtrength is as ſmoake that vaniſheth away? If God findes no ſtedfaſtneſſe in his Angels, how much leſſe in them that dwell in houſes of clay, whoſe foundation is in the duſt, which are cruſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Moth? Such as was the ſplendor of <hi>Herods</hi> robes,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:27"/> when hee was eaten of wormes and gaue vp the ghoſt, in compariſon of the brightneſſe of the Sun, ſuch is the glory of man in the preſence of God, and that ſmall luſtre which he hath in this world, is accompanied with thouſands of briers and incommodities, like a gloe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme in the midſt of a buſh. What thinke ye is the higheſt heauen before God? It is as a point in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; and what is the earth in regard of heauen, but as a point in compariſon? And what is a man in compariſon of the whole earth, but as a Piſmire wandring in a large countrey? as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Chapter 40. ſpeaketh, <hi>Behold the nations are as a drop
<pb facs="tcp:176715:27"/> of a Bueket, and are counted as the ſmall duſt of the ballance, and are as nothing before him.</hi> And therefore <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaith, <hi>Behold I haue taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to ſpeake vnto the Lord, which am but duſt and aſhes.</hi> It is alſo the end for the which God hath created man of the duſt, to the end that if he ſhould happen to glory of the light of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, hee ſhould be preſently abaſed and abated by the remembrance of the birth and beginning of his body, and by the feeling of his infirmity; and to the end hee ſhould vſe and imploy this reaſon to pray vnto God, who lifteth the poore from the duſt, and powreth his treaſures into earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:28"/> that he would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt duſt, nor enter into an accompt with aſhes; that he would let it diſſolue by nature, without diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it before his time by the violence of his wrath. This is the conſideration which <hi>Dauid</hi> brings in the 103. Pſalme, to moue God to clemency and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Like as a father pittieth his children, ſo the Lord pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them that feare him; for he knoweth our frame, he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth that we are duſt,</hi> before whom wee cannot preſent our ſelues, but our haires muſt ſtare, our blood muſt freeze within vs, and all the pride wee haue in vs muſt needes be abated by feare.</p>
               <p>All theſe conſiderations
<pb facs="tcp:176715:28"/> might make this priuate fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie of <hi>Abraham</hi> with God, ſeeme to be exceſſiue, as intending to controule the actions of God; and his cunning with ſmall reſpect to inſinuate himſelfe little by little, and obtaine by pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that which hee durſt not demand all at once.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding in that God heareth him willingly, and accepts his demaund, hinders vs to preſume of any euill in ſuch an holy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſeruant of God.</p>
               <p>To reſolue you of this point, ye muſt know that in a great ſimilitude of words, there is often a great diſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of ſence and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Two perſons ſometimes will vſe the ſame words, and
<pb facs="tcp:176715:29"/> make the ſame ſignes, but to diuers ends, and with dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent intentions. As in the 17. Chapter of Geneſis, <hi>Abraham</hi> laughes at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe which God made him touching a Sonne, this laughter in him is not repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe it proceeded of ioy, not of diſtruſt; but in the 18. Chapter <hi>Sarah</hi> laughes at the ſelfe ſame thing, and is checked for it, becauſe God did perceiue therein her diſtruſt, as if the thing was impoſſible. <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie</hi> the father of <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> and the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> doe anſwere the Angel in words alike, ſaying, <hi>How ſhall this be?</hi> In <hi>Zacharie</hi> it was a <hi>How</hi> of doubt, in the holy virgin <hi>Mary</hi> it was a <hi>How</hi> of inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:29"/> to demand inſtruction. Who could approue in any other then in <hi>Moſes</hi> theſe bolde words, <hi>Yet now if thou wilt, forgiue their ſinne, if not, blot mee I pray thee out of thy booke which thou haſt written?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You know that <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Ieremie</hi> preſt with anguiſh, haue curſed the day of their birth. I thinke that thoſe that are tormented in hell, ſay the very ſame thing; for as Chriſt ſaith of <hi>Iudas,</hi> it had beene good for thoſe men, that they had neuer beene borne. But other was the motion that droue theſe holy men to this, other the murmuring of the damned; for theſe are moued and ſet on with hatred againſt God,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:30"/> but <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Ieremie</hi> haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered themſelues to ſlippe by infirmitie to theſe words of exceſſe, wherein I doubt not but they haue greatly offended God, and haue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him pardon thereof. The bubling of their anguiſh haue caſted forth for once this ſcumme of their impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; So in a man weaker in faith then <hi>Abraham,</hi> and leſſe accuſtomed to conferre with God familiarly, this priuate familiarity might ſeeme exceſſiue; but the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility whereby he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth himſelfe duſt and aſhes, and the fauourable anſweres of God to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, doe exempt him from the crime of teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176715:30"/>
               <p>Let vs not impute to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty this kinde of inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe ſo by degrees, nor looke for any craft ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; let vs rather attribute it to the nature of faith, which imboldeneth her ſelfe by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and maketh her ſelfe familiar little by little, by how much ſhee acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the effects of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour; for the firſt fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble anſwers doe giue liberty to make others, the firſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God doe containe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert promiſes of increaſing of graces; for God giueth becauſe he hath giuen, his firſt liberalities doe inuite the following ones, hee crownes not our merits but his gifts, his gifts and his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling are without repentance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176715:31"/>
               <p>This priuate familiarity of <hi>Abraham</hi> therefore, was without contempt, his bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was modeſt; his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence humble; which hee teſtifies in acknowledging himſelfe duſt and aſhes, for without this humility his prayer had beene vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God, who reiects the prayer of the proud, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines his care vnto thoſe that haue a contrite and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſpirit, as it is ſaid in Iſaiah, Chapter 66. <hi>I will looke to him that is poore and of a contrite ſpirit, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth at my word.</hi> God ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth raine in greater abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on low places, yea, &amp; when it doth fall on high places it ſtayes not there. And if any great tempeſt
<pb facs="tcp:176715:31"/> or furious ſtorme happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the Oake and Aſhe trees are ouerthrowne and caſt downe to the earth, but the Time and Marioram re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine whole. Gods graces falling vpon the proud doe not ſtop nor ſettle there; God reſiſteth the proud, but giueth grace vnto the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: To aske of God graces with a haughty ſpirit, and opinion of his owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, is to be like him that ſhould begge with a ſuit of cloath of gold and all perfumed; he that askes after ſuch an vndecent manner muſt looke to be refuſed.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding in this gradation of <hi>Abrahams</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ands, conſidering that he being come to the number
<pb facs="tcp:176715:32"/> of ten, he ſtayes there, and ſaith not, but Lord if there be fiue found within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wilt thou not ſpare the place for thoſe fiue righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? Whither it was becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> did iudge in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that hee ought to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the decree and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the iuſtice of God, and acknowledged that it was a iuſt thing that a great Citie in the which ten righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous men were not to be found, ſhould be deſtroyed, and that hee ought not to make interceſſion for it: Or whither it was, becauſe God hindered him to proceede on in his demands, leaſt hee ſhould aske things contrary to Gods decree and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and that thereupon
<pb facs="tcp:176715:32"/> God ſhould haue been faine to haue refuſed him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect his prayer; for often in the Scripture God forbids his ſeruants to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for ſuch and ſuch, when hee is reſolued not to pardon them; he forbids <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> to pray for <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Ieremie</hi> to make interceſſion for the Iewes, becauſe God holdes it not conuenient to his goodneſſe, to permit his children to pray vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and without reaping ſome fruit.</p>
               <p>Obſerue alſo that in this conference of God with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and often elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, the faithfull are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>righteous,</hi> not that they are without ſinne, but in compariſon of the wicked;
<pb facs="tcp:176715:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> and becauſe God wipeth out their ſinnes by his mercy for his Sonnes ſake, whom <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> calleth <hi>the Lord, our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, Ieremie</hi> 23. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo becauſe of the righteouſneſſe of the cauſe, which they maintaine, and for the which cauſe they are perſecuted: So <hi>Noah, Lot, Iob, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Zacharie</hi> are called righteous, though <hi>Noab</hi> fell into drunkenneſſe, <hi>Lot</hi> committed inceſt, <hi>Dauid</hi> adultery and murther, <hi>Iob</hi> curſed the day of his birth, <hi>Zachrie</hi> doubted of Gods promiſes; which faults are as warts in a faire face, which ſeeme as an expoſition of this word <hi>Righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That we may know, that when Chriſt Ieſus ſaith that
<pb facs="tcp:176715:33"/> hee is not come for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but to call ſinners to repentance, theſe ſinners are righteous in ſome ſort, and that Ieſus Chriſt by the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous</hi> vnderſtands thoſe that thinke they are without ſin. Our righteouſneſſe conſiſts in acknowledging our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, and in cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing our ſelues with the righteouſnes of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>who hath beene made ſinne for vs, that wee might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. <hi>By his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhall my righteous ſeruant iuſtifie many</hi> Iſa. 53. <hi>Who of God is made vnto vs wiſedome, and righteouſneſſe, and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, &amp; redemption,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.</p>
               <p>This is the ſence and meaning of this hiſtory, and
<pb facs="tcp:176715:34"/> the expoſition of the three points which wee haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto you; whence ſpringeth diuers doctrines, that ſerue to comfort, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, and to humble vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>The Application.</head>
               <p>FIrſt in the manner wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God proceeds againſt <hi>Sodome,</hi> you haue an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and patterne of Gods patience, ſoliciting ſinners to repentance; he ſends <hi>Lot</hi> to thoſe of <hi>Sodome,</hi> who was among them an Herald and Preacher of righteouſneſſe, who dwelling among them, vexed his righteous ſoule from day to day with their vnlawfull deeds, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. But they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued
<pb facs="tcp:176715:34"/> him not, Gen, 19.9. <hi>This one fellow came in to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourne, and ſo will needes be a Iudge?</hi> After <hi>Lots</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, God ſends them wars, that ſpoiles their Countrey, and leads them into captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whence being deliuered by <hi>Abrahams</hi> helpe, they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend not. At the laſt God being prouoked, ſends fire from heauen, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes them: whereunto ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the nature of the ſoile, for the countrey was full of ſlime pits, which ſerued as matter vnto it, and brought a ſudden inflaming.</p>
               <p>Three things are happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto them for examples, and are written for our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, vpon whom the ends of the world are come,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:35"/> leaſt we ſhould abuſe Gods patience, who hath ſo long time ſupported vs, ſolicites &amp; calls vs to repentance: for what hath not God done, to binde vs to his loue and feare? He hath ſent vs his ſeruants, and ſet his word before our eyes, he hath cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed vs often, and hath ſet vs on foote againe by his helpe; he hath ſcattered vs in ſtrange countreys, and then re-aſſembled vs toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe by his mercy. He makes vs to ſubſiſt now as the remainder of the maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre, as ſome plankes ſaued from ſhipwracke, or like a brand reſerued from the fire, and doe as yet ſubſiſt as a miracle to ſtrangers, and a rare example of his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;
<pb facs="tcp:176715:35"/> for in the troubles of a State it happeneth ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily as with catarres and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluctions, which alwayes fall vpon the weakeſt part. Now the weakeſt part in the body of this kingdome is the Church of God, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in theſe laſt ſtirres which haue troubled this eſtate, God hath ſecured and ſaued harmeles his Church, and reſtrained the peoples will, though on our ſide we haue enough contributed to our owne ruine, and yet God euen this day giueth vs this grace, that we are here aſſembled in peace, to lift vp together our hands and hearts before his preſence. He may then ſay that which he ſaith, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5. <hi>What could
<pb facs="tcp:176715:36"/> haue beene done more to the vineyard, that I haue not done in it? Wherefore when I looked that it ſhould bring forth grapes, it brought forth wilde grapes:</hi> For that we doe not bring forth fruit worthy of repentance, is it becauſe we haue not beene chaſtiſed? but wee newly come forth out of perſecution: Or is it becauſe he hath not threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs? but yet euen now we were at deaths dore, and as it were on the point of our ſteepe downe-fall: Or is it becauſe he hath imparted vnto vs his gifts and graces ſo ſparingly? but who can comprehend his goodneſſe towards vs, his liberalitie and his patience? Or is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you haue not beene
<pb facs="tcp:176715:36"/> ſufficiently and carefully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed? but ſurely we haue not ſpared our ſelues in this point, yea, our liberty and freedome of reprehending ſeemes intollerable vnto many. After a continuall labour, we receiue inſtead of recompence, calumnies, which tend to make our Miniſtery vnfruitfull, and to take away the efficacy from our preaching: The time will come (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f GOD hath not pitty on vs) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ye ſhall haue teachers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your deſire, or elſe ſhall haue leaſure to faſt after the Word of God.</p>
               <p>But if we ſpeake in our exhortations againſt the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes of Popery, ye heare that with great attention,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:37"/> but yee will not enter into diſputation with your own vices, as being at agreement with the diuell on that ſide. You condemne the Church of Rome, in that ſhe forbids the people the reading of the holy Scripture, but are we for all that the careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to reade it? they are hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to reade it by ſcruple, but you by contempt and negligence. Ye blame thoſe that pray, not vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding what they ſay; but are ye more excuſable to pray without thinking what yee ſay? You reprehend them for ſuperſtitious ſignes and geſture that they haue in the Church; but you in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding ſuperſtition fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to irreuerence, one keeping
<pb facs="tcp:176715:37"/> on his Hat in Prayer time: another makes difficulty to kneele, to ſhew vnto our aduerſaries that wee neede not ſuffer ſo much for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſeeing we haue it in ſo litle eſteeme. You condemne the idolatry of the Church of Rome, and notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you idolatrize, and as it were worſhip your bodies and goods, which you ſerue much more and better then you ſerue God. You con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne ſpirituall whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and you pollute your ſelues with corporall forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. You condemne thoſe that eſteeme to merit Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe by their good works, &amp; in the meane time you liue as if you would go into hel by your euill workes, or as
<pb facs="tcp:176715:38"/> hoping to be ſaued without your good workes. Wee blame auricular confeſſion, but are we for all that now carefull to confeſſe our ſinnes to God? Wee blame thoſe that thinke to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme their ſinnes by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney giuen to the Church, but the money we ſpare on that ſide, is it beſtowed in almes-deedes? and that which we withdraw from the idle, is it conſecrated to Gods ſeruice. Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe the poore languiſh and accuſe the rich to be little charitable, the cry of the poore is mounted and entred into the cares of the LORD of hoſtes.</p>
               <p>And therefore doe not take it as an iniurie to be
<pb facs="tcp:176715:38"/> compared to Sodome and Gomorrah; for although we are guiltleſſe of that ſin, for the which God conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them with fire; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinnes that cry as loude as that, and for the which many hearers of the Word of God, ſhal be more rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled in the day of Iudgement then Sodome and Gomorrah, as it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced vnto Capernaum, Corazin, and Bethſaida, Mat. 11. that had ſeene the miracles of Ieſus Chriſt, and heard his word, which they had reiected, and were not conuerted.</p>
               <p>And indeed the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth vs, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the ſinne of Sodome,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:39"/> there are other ſinnes that cry and call for the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of God. There is the cry of the innocent bloud, witneſſe the bloud of <hi>Abel,</hi> that cryed from the earth vnto God. There is the cry of the labourers and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, whoſe hire is kept backe by fraude, whereof Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, Iam. 5.4. There is the cry of the widdow, and of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan, whereof <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, Exod. 22. <hi>Yee ſhall not afflict any widdow, or father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe childe, if thou afflict them in any wiſe, and they cry at all vnto me, I will ſurely heare their cry, and my wrath ſhall waxe hot, and I will kill you with the ſword, and your wiues ſhall be widdowes, and your
<pb facs="tcp:176715:39"/> children fatherleſſe.</hi> Which is a ſinne that is to be found among vs, beſides which, example of violent ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and vſury are to be found. Such a one faſteth this day from fleſh and meat, that eateth at his houſe the fleſh of the poore, and conſumeth his neighbours ſubſtance. Many ouertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Gods commandement that forbids to come vnto the altar with voide hands, bring to the Lords Table hands full of violence and extortion, farre from cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Ieſus Chriſt in his members, ſeeing that they ſtrip them thereof.</p>
               <p>And what thinke yee of the mortall, or rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall quarrels of thoſe,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:40"/> that haue not learnt to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, that aske of God euery day that hee forgiue them not their ſinnes, ſeeing they forgiue not thoſe that haue treſpaſſed againſt them; that hate a thouſand times more their neighbour, then they loue God; ſeeing they defame the Church of God by their quarrels, and put it to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſhame? What, doe yee thinke that theſe things cry not againſt heauen? Doe ye thinke that the Heathen ſouldiers, hauing not torne Chriſts coate, thoſe can be ſuffered that teare his body, which is the Church? and ſeeing that he who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth one of the leaſt ones, deſerues to be thrown and drowned in the depth
<pb facs="tcp:176715:40"/> of the Sea, with a milſtone about his necke, hee which offends the whole Church, deſerues he not to be caſt into Hell? Or do ye thinke that he can haue peace with his father, that is alwayes in quarrell with his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren?</p>
               <p>It is good alſo to obſerue the cauſes of the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sodome, and by what degrees ſhe came to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. The Prophet <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel,</hi> tels vs in the 16. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Behold, this was the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of thy Siſter Sodome, pride, fulneſſe of bread, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of idleneſſe, neither did ſhe ſtrengthen the hand of the poore and needy.</hi> Theſe ſelfe-ſame vices doe infect our flocke; charity dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth
<pb facs="tcp:176715:41"/> amongſt vs, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe increaſeth; the quarrels are hot, and the prayers cold; the word of GOD ill planted in our hearts, rancour and hatred firmely rooted in them; the parents are careful to hoord vp goods for their children, but not to teach them to make good vſe of them, and to forgoe them willingly for the Goſpels ſake. In poore families, you ſhall find in an extream pouerty, an extreame pride, idlenes &amp; drunkennes; they had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee their children go na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, then apply themſelues to labour and ſobriety. Yee ſhall ſee in many of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility a prophane humour, an arrogant ignorance, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane
<pb facs="tcp:176715:41"/> and filthy words, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſwearing, a diſtaſte of Gods Word. They are couragious to reuenge their owne iniuries, but cowards to reſiſt their vices, or to defend Gods cauſe; ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in cloathes, but nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards in almes-deeds. They are not ſuch as our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were in olde time, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to run to Martyrdome, but they are ready to runne to euery publike faction and ſedition.</p>
               <p>Are theſe thoſe, whom God hath raiſed to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prop &amp; ſupport his Church? or doe we hope that God will deliuer his people by their hands?</p>
               <p>Of all in generall wee make this complaint, with
<pb facs="tcp:176715:42"/> the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 9. <hi>The people turneth not vnto him that ſmiteth them neither doe they ſeeke the LORD of hoſtes.</hi> Thou haſt ſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them, and they haue felt no paine; thou haſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed them and they haue refuſed to receiue inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they haue hardened their faces like ſtone, they haue refuſed to turne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; and as it is in the 29. Chapter of <hi>Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: They haue bleſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their hearts,</hi> that is to ſay, flattered themſelues, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I ſhal haue peace, though I walk in the imagination &amp; ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornes of mine heart, to adde drunkennes to thirſt.</hi> By this meanes Gods patience, that ſhould ſerue to amend vs,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:42"/> ſerues to marre vs. God will giue vs thereby leaſure to repent vs of our ſinnes, and we take leaſure thereby to reioyce in our wickednes. God commands vs to be holy, but we will make him a ſinner, winking at our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane humour. Hee will haue vs expect his helpe, and we will haue him expect our amendment at our leaſure. This is the right brimſtone that puls downe fire from heauen, that ſulphurous earth of Sodome neuer had ſuch force, to draw downe Gods inflaming anger con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming them with fire, as the contempt of Gods Word hath power to pull downe his iudgements on our heads: Let vs feare
<pb facs="tcp:176715:43"/> leaſt his patience being in the ende ouercome by his wrath, we find no more place of repentance, as Godthreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by his Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 1. <hi>Therefore when you ſpread foorth your hands, I will hide mine eies from you, yea, when ye make many prayers, I will not heare.</hi> But as for them that turne themſelues vnto the LORD. Gods familiarity with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the free acceſſe he giues to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, ought to giue them a holy confidence to ſpeak vnto God familiarly, and to be aſſured that God will heare them. For as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. that that which is written of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, which was imputed to him for
<pb facs="tcp:176715:43"/> righteouſneſſe, <hi>Was not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for his ſake alone, but for vs alſo, to whom it ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, if we beleeue on him that raiſed vp Ieſus our Lord from the dead.</hi> So then hold certainely, that this benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our God in hearing <hi>Abrahams</hi> demaunds, that ſeemed to be importunate, is not propounded onely for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſake; but for you alſo that beleeue, that yee may haue this aſſurance, that God is euen delighted and deſires to be impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned by his children, and is not offended with this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall freedome, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes from the ſpirit of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption; that he loues this holy obſtinacy; who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Iacob</hi> wraſtling with
<pb facs="tcp:176715:44"/> him, lets him not goe, till it hath got a bleſſing; or after the example of the woman of Canaan, who being often repulſed by Ieſus Chriſt, yea euen ſo far as to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by him to a dogge, yet at laſt ſhe obtaines, beſides the curing of her daughter, this teſtimonie of Chriſt that her faith was great, and that hee had not found ſo great a faith, no not in Iſrael. And this is that ſpirit of adoption, of freeneſſe and libertie, which makes, that as in afflictions wee had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fall into the hands of God, then into the hands of men, becauſe his compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are great and many; ſo in matter of demands and requeſts we dare aske of him
<pb facs="tcp:176715:44"/> ſuch things, as we dare not aske of men, becauſe his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and goodneſſe are accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his greatneſſe, that is to ſay, are incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
               <p>Nay, which is more, to giue vs the more priuate fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity to call vpon him, although he doth vs good by his free-will, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conſtraint; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he will haue vs to thinke that he giues it to our importunity and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in prayer, as wee are taught by our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. by that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of a friend that goes vnto his friend at midnight, and ſayes vnto him; friend, lend me three Loaues, I ſay vnto you, ſaith Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:45"/> though hee will not riſe and giue him, becauſe he is his friend, yet becauſe of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, he will riſe and giue him as many as he nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; and by the example of an vniuſt Iudge, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcheth the poore widdow of her ſuit to deliuer himſelfe from her importunitie, whence Chriſt ſaith, Shall not God auenge his owne elect, which cry day and night vnto him, though he beare long with them?</p>
               <p>This confidence and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity of praying vnto God, ſhall no more barre humility, then it did in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> who amiddeſt his requeſts, full of liberty, acknowledgeth himſelfe notwithſtanding to bee
<pb facs="tcp:176715:45"/> naught but duſt and aſhes. There is an humble famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity, an humility with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which being drawne to by loue, diminiſheth not the reuerence due vnto him. Wherefore in prayer wee ioyne together theſe two geſtures, we bow our knees, and lift vp our eyes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the one witneſſeth our humility, the other our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence. Many other do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines doe ariſe from this Text, which we will briefly touch. When you reade that in a great city, ten righteous are not to be found among many thouſands; you may learne, that you muſt not ſquare your ſelfe by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to liue well, as the LORD ſaith, Exod. 23.
<pb facs="tcp:176715:46"/> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to doe euill.</hi> The multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude hath been alwayes a bad counſellor, the broad way leades to deſtruction. The whole world, ſhall run after and follow the beaſt, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 13. They that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the greatneſſe, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and vniuerſality for markes of the Church, had they liued in Sodome, would haue ſooner ioyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the Sodomites, then with <hi>Lot,</hi> who was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt alone among this mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
               <p>Which <hi>Lot</hi> being righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, of whom <hi>Abraham</hi> ſpeaketh, when hee ſaith, wilt thou deſtroy the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous with the wicked? tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs by his example,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:46"/> that it is a dangerous thing for an holy man to liue in the company of the wicked. Wherefore <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, Pſal. 26. <hi>Gather not my ſoule with ſinners, nor my life with bloudy men.</hi> One <hi>Ionas</hi> thinking to eſcape and fly from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, and to exempt himſelfe from his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, had like to haue caſt away the whole ſhip. A hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Captaine of a ſhip, hearing a wicked man ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his prayer among the reſt during the tempeſt, Hold thy peace, ſaith he, and hide thy ſelfe, leſt the gods know that thou art heere. Wherefore God ſaide vnto the Iſraelites, depart from the tents of theſe wicked men; namely, <hi>Korah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176715:47"/> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and touch nothing of theirs, leaſt ye be conſumed in all their ſinnes: Come out of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes, and that ye receiue not of her plagues; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not onely for feare of the like peril &amp; puniſhment, but alſo for feare of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of vices. There is nothing ſo glewiſh as euill examples, nothing ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious as the company of the wicked. If <hi>Dina</hi> had not haunted dancing, ſhee had preſerued her chaſtity. If the Iſraelites in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time had not allied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by marriage with the infidels, their children ſhould not haue ſpoken the
<pb facs="tcp:176715:47"/> language of Aſhdod. A little leauen leaueneth the whole lumpe, by the conuerſation and acquaintance with the wicked, wee become like them. Wherefore euen as one counſelleth women that conceiue, to haue by their bed ſide the pictures of faire children, ſo muſt we haue faire examples before our eyes, to the end we may conceiue good thoughts, and bring forth good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>For what concord hath Chriſt with Belial? or what part hath hee that belieueth with an Infidell? wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeparated<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aith the LORD, and touch not the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Finally touching that
<pb facs="tcp:176715:48"/> which you haue heard; namely, if there had beene tenne righteous men in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, God would haue ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Citie for their ſakes; ye may learne how God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemeth his children, chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rather the preſeruation of ten of his children, then the ruine of ten thouſands of his enemies. He beares with the wickedneſſe of the world, and fore ſlowes his iudgements for his Church ſake mixed with the world; ſo God would not ſend the floud till after <hi>Methuſalems</hi> death, who dyed a yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the floud; as ſoone as <hi>Ioſias</hi> is dead, <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> inuadeth the countrey of <hi>Iudea;</hi> the life of one ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God did ſupport
<pb facs="tcp:176715:48"/> the countrey, and keepe backe Gods iudgements. So ſoone as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was dead, the Citie Bona, whereof hee was Biſhop, was wonne by the Vandals, and ſacked by them; as if by the death of that good man of God, the rampiers and walles of the towne were fallen downe. Therefore the LORD in the 57. Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> after he had ſaide, that the righteous man peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, and no man layeth it to heart, and mercifull men are taken away; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after hee makes the puniſhment of the wicked to follow, as a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſequele and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. <hi>But draw ye hither yee ſonnes of the Sorcereſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:49"/> againſt whom doe ye ſpore your ſelues? &amp;c.</hi> Nay which is more, God hauing lifted vp his hand, to turne vpſide downe heauen and earth, becauſe they are become a temple of idols, and the kingdome of the deuill, is ſtopped and withheld from doing it, becauſe there are a few of the faithfull mingled among the wicked, leaſt in rooting vp the darnell, hee ſhould alſo plucke vp by the rootes the good corne; therefore it is ſaid to the ſoules of them that were ſlaine for the Word of God, that were vnder the altar, and cryed for vengeance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them that dwell on earth, <hi>Apocal.</hi> 6. that they ſhould reſt yet for a little
<pb facs="tcp:176715:49"/> ſeaſon, vntill their fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and their brethren that ſhould be killed as they were, ſhould be fulfilled; that being once done, the end of the world will neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily follow: for ſhould the world be ſo poſſeſt by the diuell that God ſhould haue no part in it? or ſhould the Sunne riſe onely to giue light to thoſe that doe euill? It is therefore one of the reaſons, for the which the faithfull are called the ſalt of the earth, Matth. 5. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is that part that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues the reſt of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the earth, and protects the world from corruption.</p>
               <p>And to apply theſe things to our ſelues, I eſteeme that
<pb facs="tcp:176715:50"/> theſe laſt dayes paſt, when our Churches were in great danger, God caſt his eyes vpon vs; hee conſidered therein many miſchiefes and maladies that infect the flocke; that couetouſneſſe is very riſe among vs, ſo that wee eſteeme of men as wee eſteeme of bagges of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, that is to ſay, according to the money they haue, the man is eſteemed as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as the bagge is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing eſteemed. That euery one tels lyes and liues ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his neighbour. That deſtruction, hatred, ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are among vs, in the higheſt degree; that vſury, whoredome, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are to be found among vs, to the great diſhonour
<pb facs="tcp:176715:50"/> of the Goſpell, that ſo ſoone as there is neuer ſo little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, exceſſe, not and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity of apparell doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently appeare; and that charity towards the poore, and the zeale of the honour of God is waxed colde; while as the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious powere out their goods at the feete of an Idoll, doe lay foundations of new reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, build Churches, giue offrings, buy maſſes and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices at a great rate and with an extreame coſt; that is to ſay, that ſuperſtition is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent in them, but true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion key-cold in vs; that they to make a molten Calfe, doe contribute euen vnto their iewels and golden eare-rings, whiles that the ſeruice of the
<pb facs="tcp:176715:51"/> honour of God is ill main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
               <p>For theſe cauſes he had already ſent his deſtroying Angels, and had ſnatcht a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his word from vs, had it not beene that euen hee the ſame vnto whom <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſpake, who is his onely Sonne our Lord and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus hath ſtayed his wrath, and therevpon hee hath conſidered ten righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous amidſt this corruption, that is to ſay, ſome few of the number of the true faithfull, and of holy ſoules that feare him, and groane vnder the generall corruption; for whoſe ſake he ſuſpends as yet his iudgements, and ſpares the flocke; and thoſe perhaps not the greateſt
<pb facs="tcp:176715:51"/> ones, nor the richeſt, nor the moſt noble; but perhaps ſome poore, whom we know not, and to whom we, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull, con little thankes; He hath ſtopt and ſtayed Gods iudgements, and hath ſtood in the gap, and hath beene in the publicke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, like the lifting vp of the hands of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that did more then <hi>Ioſuahs</hi> ſword; which is the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the <hi>wiſe-man</hi> makes in the 9. of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> That there was a little City and few men within it, and there came a great King againſt it, and beſieged it, and built great bulwarkes againſt it; now there was found in it a poore <hi>wiſe-man,</hi> and he by his wiſedome deliuered the
<pb facs="tcp:176715:52"/> City, yet no man remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that poore man.</p>
               <p>Seing then that the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe that feare the Lord among vs, is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and the ſafety of the Church, and as King <hi>Ioram</hi> ſaid of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> the Chariot of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the horſemen thereof, for whoſe ſake God pardoneth the reſt: Let vs labour to increaſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them; and that notten not thirty, not fifty, but that the whole troupe and flocke be truely the holy nation and the portion of the Lord. Let vs make our ſinnes hold their peace that cry, and that their crie be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with the crye of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which powres vnto the feete of our Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,
<pb facs="tcp:176715:52"/> that precious ointment, with an holy griefe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewes them with herteares as heretofore <hi>Mary</hi> did, whoſe teares were a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more odorife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, then her precious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for this filled the chamber with a ſweet plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſmell, but her repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is euen yet of good fauour in the Church of God.</p>
               <p>And in ſtead of that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy burthen of ſinnes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Chriſt Ieſus doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge vs, Let vs charge and take vpon vs his yoake which is eaſie, and his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then which is light; whether by this yoake and burthen we vnderſtand his croſſe; or whether wee take it in
<pb facs="tcp:176715:53"/> generall for our ſubiection vnto his word; that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after we haue no other will then his, no other truſt and confidence then in his promiſes, no other ioy then in his loue.</p>
               <p>And that wee may make vſe of our vices, and giue to our deſires a lawfull imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and occupation; let not the violent haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after any other violence, then that which taketh by force the Kingdome of heauen. Let vſurers giue themſelues to giuing to the poore, for that is to lend vnto God by vſury. Let the couerous gather a treaſure in heauen. Let the quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers make an irreconcillable warre againſt their vices.
<pb facs="tcp:176715:53"/> Let the haughty and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious glory in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and in that they are the children of the moſt high.</p>
               <p>If ye doe ſo, God who deſires not the death of a ſinner, but his conuerſion, whoſe compaſſions are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies open towards thoſe that ſeeke him; will watch for your ſafegard; hee will blow vpon the enterprizes of our enemies, and will fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate their hopes; his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence ſhall be as a wall of fire about his Church. If you feare GOD, you will not feare men. Beare your ſelues couragious againſt mens threatnings, but trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at Gods Word, who hath bought and redeemed you
<pb facs="tcp:176715:54"/> with too great a price, to leaue you. He will not deny you things neceſſary for this preſent life, ſeeing that from the foundation of the world he hath prepared for you an euerlaſting kingdome; as he himſelfe will proclaime in the laſt day. <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, inherito the kingdome prepared for you, from the foundation of the world.</hi> To whom be aſcribed all honour, power and dominion, for euer and euer, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
